Duncan Emrich Manuscript Collection, 1933-1977
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
- Series 2: Correspondence
  - Walton, Richard Guy. January 24, 1975 Permission request., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/81)
  - Warner, Frank. January 16, 1971 Response to Emrich’s requesting permission to include songs which Warner recorded., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/82)
  - West, John O. to Heather Newman. 1976 Correspondence about Emrich’s conversation with the Editor of the American Folklore Society Journal, John West, sent to Heather Newman, the President of the Junior Folklore Club. Included is the 1976 Fall issue of the journal which has a blurb about the club, along with announcement of Alan Jabbour’s position as Head of the American Folklife Center., 5 pages (Box-folder 2/83)
  - Western Folklore (S.J. Sackett Book, Review Editor). June, 1968; January, 1971 Emrich requests permission to cite works from two folklore journals., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/84)
  - William Morris Agency, Inc. 1966-1969 Book proposals and contracts., 8 pages. (Box-folder 2/85)
  - Yale University Press. February 10, 1971 Response to Emrich’s request to use the ballad "Captain Ward and the Rainbow.", 1 page. (Box-folder 2/86)
  - Linda. April 3, 1972 Personal correspondence., 1 page. (Box-folder 3/87)
  - Book of Death. Undated Correspondence pertaining to the unfinished Book of Death., 27 pages. (Box-folder 3/88)
  - Whim Wham Book. 1976-1977 Correspondence pertaining to The Whim Wham Book., 5 pages. (Box-folder 3/89)
  - The Junior Folklore Club of America. August, 1976 Junior Folklore Club organization., 1 page. (Box-folder 3/90)
  - Jerry. Undated Correspondence concerning the Junior Folklore Club., 1 page. (Box-folder 3/91)
  - Little, Brown and Company Publishers, Dianne M. Muller. Undated Form for book review., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/92)
  - Proposal for Book: Calories Do Count. Undated Justification for book proposal., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/93)
  - AMS Press, Inc., Lee Hatfield. May 27, 1977 Permission to use Vance Randolph's work., 1 page. (Box-folder 3/94)
  - Various postcards. Undated, 4 pages. (Box-folder 3/95)
  - Unaddressed documents along with the dust jacket for Duncan Emrich’s book, It’s An Old Wild West Custom. Undated, 6 pages. (Box-folder 3/96)
- Series 3: Personal Papers
  - Military Documents. Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force. 1943-1945 Various documents pertaining to Emrich’s service with SHAEF. Including written orders, passes and other official military papers., 52 pages. (Box-folder 4/97)
  - Department of State: United States Information Service. 1947; 1962 Official pages pertaining to Emrich’s appointed position as cultural officer., 8 pages. (Box-folder 4/98)
  - Curriculum Vitae. Resumes Undated. Several resumes from throughout Emrich’s career., 15 pages. (Box-folder 4/99)
  - Fan Letters (1 of 2) Letters from readers of Emrich’s books, mainly from children., 106 pages. (Box-folder 4/100)
  - Fan Letter (2 of 2) Letters from readers of Emrich’s books, mainly from children., 26 pages. (Box-folder 4/101)
  - Book Review of Folklore International Essays in Honor of Wayland Debs Hand in Western Folklore 28 (January, 1969); 52-53., 3 pages. (Box-folder 4/102)
  - Reviews of Emrich’s Books Originals and photocopies., 56 pages. (Box-folder 4/103)
  - Typescript on Thomas Wolfe Photocopy of pages 1-63., 27 pages. (Box-folder 4/104)
  - Passport. May 10, 1933 Contains original United States passport belonging to Emrich., 16 pages. (Box-folder 4/105)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities. Fellowship Forms Includes official forms., 20 pages. (Box-folder 4/106)
  - Harvard University Transcript, 1934-37 Dated May 21, 1968., 1 page. (Box-folder 4/107)
  - Leiding, Harriette Kershaw, "Street Cries of an Old Southern City," 1910. (Charlestown, S.C., Privately Published) A copy of the front matter and chapter that was used in Folklore on the American Land., 11 pages. (Box-folder 4/108)
  - Copy of Roger Abrahams, "Some Riddles from the Negro of Philadelphia." Keystone Folklore Quarterly 7, no. 4 (Winter 1962): 10-16., 7 pages. (Box-folder 4/109)
  - Copy of Herbert Halpert’s, "Negro Riddles Collected in New Jersey." Journal of American Folklore 56, no. 221 (July-September 1943): 200-202., 3 pages. (Box-folder 4/110)
  - Copy of Ernest W. Baughman, "Folk Sayings and Beliefs." New Mexico Folklore Record 9 (1954-55): 23-27., 5 pages. (Box-folder 4/111)
  - Brown University, Transcript. 1925-1932 Includes transcript., 2 pages. (Box-folder 4/112)
  - Lewis, Mark B. Letter of Recommendations Includes recommendation letters., 2 pages. (Box-folder 4/113)
  - University of Nevada, Faculty Positions. April 4, 1969 Includes position announcement., 1 page. (Box-folder 4/114)
  - The New Mexico Folklore Record (1969-70) Includes publication announcement., 1 page. (Box-folder 4/115)
  - "The Oxyrrhynchos Papyri: "Menenius Apius to Attilius Navious. Translation by Constantine D. Tsatsos. Original and photocopies., 50 pages. (Box-folder 4/116)
  - Veloudios, Thanos A.D. "The Kalikantzari." Pictures from Greece (January, 1957) Original newsprint and photocopies., 10 pages. (Box-folder 4/117)
  - Magazine/Newspaper Clippings Originals and photocopies of various materials including newspaper articles pertaining to American folklore., 20 pages. (Box-folder 4/118)
  - Notebook of songs and poems A 5 x 8 in. handwritten notebook of songs and poems along with other handwritten and typed pages. On the end sheet Emrich address himself as Captain and instructs that if anyone finds the notebook it should be returned to his wife in Washington D.C. The pages were all housed within a red leather embroidered folder which can be found in Oversized Box 1., 50 pages. (Box-folder 4/119)
- Series 4: Articles
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine. 1940-1949 (1 of 2), 23 pages. (Box-folder 5/120)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine. 1940-1949 (2 of 2), 91 pages. (Box-folder 5/121)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine. 1950-1959, 95 pages. (Box-folder 5/122)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine. 1960-1969, 5 pages. (Box-folder 5/123)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine. 1970-1979, 1 page. (Box-folder 5/124)
  - Articles about Duncan Emrich. Newspaper/Magazine., 12 pages. (Box-folder 5/125)
  - Poems by Duncan Emrich. Typed and handwritten., 50 pages. (Box-folder 5/126)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich Newspapers/Magazines. Undated (1 of 2) Includes articles written by Duncan Emrich., 65 pages. (Box-folder 5/127)
  - Articles by Duncan Emrich Newspapers/Magazines. Undated. (2 of 2) Includes articles written by Duncan Emrich., 60 pages. (Box-folder 6/128)
  - "Jack and the Bull" from Jack Tales (pp. 31-53) Contains three manuscripts of "Jack and the Bull.", 69 pages. (Box-folder 6/129)
  - "Leander" Cowboy Story by Duncan Emrich. Contains the three manuscripts of "Leander" a story about a man who fought to be considered as a cowboy., 69 pages. (Box-folder 6/130)
  - "Professor Takes A Holiday" Two different drafts of "Professor Takes a Holiday." The first version is ten pages. The second version is thirty one pages. Both versions are written by Duncan Emrich., 41 pages. (Box-folder 6/131)
  - Who Shot Maggie in the Freckle? and other Ballads of Virginia City, Nevada, and articles. Includes the pamphlet and ballad Who Shot Maggie in the Freckle? and other ballads of Virginia City, Nevada composed under his pseudonym of the Comstocker. Also includes the original and photocopies articles written about Emrich and his ballad., 23 pages. (Box-folder 6/132)
- Series 5: Student Papers
  - University of Maryland Class in Folklore. 1947 (1 of 2) Assignments submitted by students for of a course taught by Emrich., 200 pages. (Box-folder 7/133)
  - University of Maryland Class in Folklore. 1947. (2 of 2) Assignments submitted by students as part of a course taught by Emrich including index cards., 200 pages. (Box-folder 7/134)
- Series 6: Published and Unpublished Works
  - American Folk Poetry. Indexes and Publishers Lists. Contains indexes organized by title, subject and first line. Also contains a list of record companies that specialize in American folksong., 183 pages. (Box-folder 8/135)
  - American Folk Poetry. Preliminary Pages, Song Lyrics #1-59 Drafts of an introduction along with numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 71 pages. (Box-folder 8/136)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #61-150 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 89 pages. (Box-folder 8/137)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #151-219 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 67 pages. (Box-folder 8/138)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #220-290 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 70 pages. (Box-folder 8/139)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #291-373 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 82 pages. (Box-folder 8/140)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #374-454 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 80 pages. (Box-folder 8/141)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #455-616 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 161 pages. (Box-folder 8/142)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #617-753 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 136 pages. (Box-folder 8/143)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #754-824 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 70 pages. (Box-folder 9/144)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #825-903 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 78 pages. (Box-folder 9/145)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #904-993 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 89 pages. (Box-folder 9/146)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #994-1051 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 57 pages. (Box-folder 9/147)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #1052-1109 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 57 pages. (Box-folder 9/148)
  - American Folk Poetry. Song Lyrics #1110-1176 Numbered sheets containing song lyrics., 66 pages. (Box-folder 9/149)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Sections 7-12, 186 pages. (Box-folder 9/150)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Sections 13-16, 128 pages. (Box-folder 9/151)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Sections 17-21, 114 pages. (Box-folder 9/152)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Section 22, 157 pages. (Box-folder 9/153)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Sacred Harp. Sections 23-24, 72 pages. (Box-folder 10/154)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Carols and Christmas Songs/War and Historical Pieces. Sections 25-27, 94 pages. (Box-folder 10/155)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Disasters and Tragedies. Sections 28-31, 147 pages. (Box-folder 10/156)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. The 49ers and Songs of the Mormons. Sections 32-36, 125 pages. (Box-folder 10/157)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. The Cowboys and Murders. Sections 37-40., 112 pages. (Box-folder 10/158)
  - American Folk Poetry. Typescript, Final. Outlaws and Bad Men, Blues, Miscellaneous and Pieces Relating to the American Land. Sections 41-44, 113 pages. (Box-folder 10/159)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 1 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 75 pages. (Box-folder 11/160)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 2 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 97 pages. (Box-folder 11/161)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 3 of 14 Typed song lyrics and photocopies., 100 pages. (Box-folder 11/162)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 4 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 93 pages. (Box-folder 11/163)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 5 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 103 pages. (Box-folder 11/164)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 6 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 77 pages. (Box-folder 11/165)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 7 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 66 pages. (Box-folder 11/166)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 8 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 110 pages. (Box-folder 11/167)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 9 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 84 pages. (Box-folder 11/168)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 10 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 88 pages. (Box-folder 11/169)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 11 of 14 Sheet music, handwritten., 99 pages. (Box-folder 12/170)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 12 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 17 pages. (Box-folder 12/171)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 13 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 100 pages. (Box-folder 12/172)
  - Anthology of American Folksong. Duncan Emrich and Charles Seeger. 14 of 14 Typed song lyrics., 179 pages. (Box-folder 12/173)
  - "A Bibliography of American Folksong in the English Language." Compiled by Joseph C. Hickerson. 1 of 2 Listing of books pertaining to American Folksong with handwritten notes., 53 pages. (Box-folder 12/174)
  - "A Bibliography of American Folksong in the English Language." Compiled by, Joseph C. Hickerson. 2 of 2 Listing of books pertaining to American Folksong with handwritten notes., 70 pages. (Box-folder 12/175)
  - Bibliography, compiled by Joseph C. Hickerson Draft of bibliography., 89 pages. (Box-folder 12/176)
  - Folklore on the American Land Typescript containing sections on name changes, rhyming, and other editorial remarks., 93 pages. (Box-folder 13/177)
  - Emrich/Dorson Controversy over Folklore on the American Land Documents pertaining to a written conflict between Dr. Emrich and Dr. Richard Dorson of Indiana University resulting from Dr. Dorson’s review of Folklore on The American Land., 7 pages. (Box-folder 13/178)
  - The Folklore of Love and Courtship Contains galleys, sample text, and book jacket., 20 pages. (Box-folder 13/179)
  - The Folklore of Weddings and Marriage Contains galleys, letters, and jacket blurbs., 15 pages. (Box-folder 13/180)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 1 of 16 Acknowledgements and other preliminary materials., 5 pages. (Box-folder 14/181)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 2 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe., 121 pages. (Box-folder 14/182)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 3 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe., 92 pages. (Box-folder 14/183)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 4 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe., 95 pages. (Box-folder 14/184)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 5 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe., 102 pages. (Box-folder 14/185)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 6 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe., 79 pages. (Box-folder 14/186)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 7 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe with handwritten notes. Contains sections for "American Legends" and the "Folklore of Manifest Destiny.", 93 pages. (Box-folder 14/187)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 8 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Includes a list of the book’s contents, the book’s forward and title pages; as well as sections organized by page number: pp. 2-38., 58 pages. (Box-folder 14/188)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 9 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp. 39-102., 64 pages. (Box-folder 14/189)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 10 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp.103-179., 75 pages. (Box-folder 14/190)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 11 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp.180-236., 69 pages. (Box-folder 14/191)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 12 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp. 238-334., 81 pages. (Box-folder 14/192)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 13 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp. 335-415., 80 pages. (Box-folder 15/193)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 14 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp. 417-494., 67 pages. (Box-folder 15/194)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 15 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains sections organized by page number: pp. 495-540., 43 pages. (Box-folder 15/195)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader. Duncan Emrich and Charles Clegg. 16 of 16 Typed articles and other works by Lucius Beebe. Contains a checklist of sources as well as sections organized by page number: pp. 541-575., 43 pages. (Box-folder 15/196)
  - Whim Wham Book. Typescript. 1 of 2 Preliminary content as well as pages 1-100., 113 pages. (Box-folder 16/197)
  - Whim Wham Book. Typescript. 2 of 2 Contains typescript of pages 107-212., 105 pages (Box-folder 16/198)
  - Whim Wham Book. Intro/Riddles/Knock Knock Jokes. 1 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 19 pages. (Box-folder 16/199)
  - Whim Wham Book. Good and Bad Luck, Abracadabra, Magic Squares, and SATOR. 2 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 28 pages. (Box-folder 16/200)
  - Whim Wham Book. Puzzles and Problems/Minute Mysteries. 3 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 14 pages. (Box-folder 16/201)
  - Whim Wham Book. Games/Jump Rope. 4 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 15 pages. (Box-folder 16/202)
  - Whim Wham Book. Teasing/Kissing Games. 5 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 28 pages. (Box-folder 16/203)
  - Whim Wham Book. Ah, Youth! 6 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 25 pages. (Box-folder 16/204)
  - Whim Wham Book. The Mail/Wishes/Autograph Albums. 7 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 42 pages. (Box-folder 16/205)
  - Whim Wham Book. Children’s Beliefs. 8 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 28 pages. (Box-folder 16/206)
  - Whim Wham Book. Proverbs and Proverbial Speech. 9 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 17 pages. (Box-folder 16/207)
  - Whim Wham Book. School/Summer Camp Songs and Cheers. 10 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 23 pages. (Box-folder 16/208)
  - Whim Wham Book. Rhymes and Tingles/Odds and Ends/Source Notes. 11 of 11 Contains typescript of the chapter., 29 pages. (Box-folder 16/209)
  - Animal Lore. Unpublished Manuscript. 1 of 2 Typed and handwritten stories and assorted lore organized by type of animal., 80 pages. (Box-folder 17/210)
  - Animal Lore. Unpublished Manuscript. 2 of 2 Typed and handwritten stories and assorted lore organized by type of animal., 80 pages. (Box-folder 17/211)
  - American Folklore for Young Americans. Marion V. Emrich, and George Korson. 1 of 2 Typed manuscript., 80 pages. (Box-folder 17/212)
  - American Folklore for Young Americans. Marion V. Emrich and George Korson. 2 of 2 Typed manuscript., 100 pages. (Box-folder 17/213)
  - The Book of Death (Unfinished) Preliminary List of Photographs., 3 pages. (Box-folder 17/214)
  - Child’s Book of Folklore. Marion V. Emrich and George Korson, second draft. 1 of 2 Typed stories and assorted lore organized by topic., 60 pages. (Box-folder 17/215)
  - Child’s Book of Folklore. Marion V. Emrich and George Korson, second draft. 2 of 2 Typed stories and assorted lore organized by topic., 60 pages. (Box-folder 17/216)
  - Child’s Book of Folklore. Marion V. Emrich and George Korson Articles, advertisements, and other ephemera pertaining to the publication of Child’s Book of Folklore (Box-folder 17/217)
  - Draft of A Book of Western Lore for Young People Typed with handwritten notes., 142 pages. (Box-folder 17/218)
  - American Folk Poetry. September 16, 1971 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 5 pages. (Box-folder 18/219)
  - The Book of Death. June 22, 1976 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 5 pages. (Box-folder 18/220)
  - The Book of Nonsense. October 15, 1968 Includes edited contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 7 pages. (Box-folder 18/221)
  - Book of Wishes. March 25, 1970 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 1 page. (Box-folder 18/222)
  - Folklore on the American Land. July 14, 1967 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 5 pages. (Box-folder 18/223)
  - The Folklore Book. September 6, 1974 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 7 pages. (Box-folder 18/224)
  - Folklore of Love and Courtship. June 12, 1969 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 1 page. (Box-folder 18/225)
  - The Hodge Podge Book. December 30, 1970 Includes contract for the book between Emrich and the publisher., 7 pages. (Box-folder 18/226)
  - The Lucius Beebe Reader. August 5, 1968 Includes edited contract between Emrich, Clegg and publisher., 8 pages. (Box-folder 18/227)
  - The Whim Wham Book. September 11, 1972 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 7 pages. (Box-folder 18/228)
  - Untitled work on the Folklore of Names and Nicknames. September 6, 1974 Includes contract for book between Emrich and the publisher., 7 pages. (Box-folder 18/229)
- Series 7: Graphic Materials
  - Graphic Images. Duncan Emrich This folder consists mainly of black-and-white photographic prints of Duncan Emrich at different stages of his life. (Box-folder 19/230)
- Oversize Materials
  - Washington’s Best Address, Diary: 1846, Untitled Poem, Nevada, Dry Land, Memorandum; S.H.A.E.F. (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Leather Folder (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Lucius Beebe Reader Page and galley proofs of the manuscript (Box-folder 21/1)